<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Game Physics on Gaffer On Games</title>
    <link>http://127.0.0.1:1313/categories/game-physics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Game Physics on Gaffer On Games</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © Glenn Fiedler, 2004 - 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://127.0.0.1:1313/categories/game-physics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Networked Physics (2004)</title>
      <link>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/networked_physics_2004/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/networked_physics_2004/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Glenn Fiedler and welcome to Game Physics.
In the previous article we discussed how to use spring-like forces to model basic collision response, joints and motors.
In this article we&amp;rsquo;re going to discuss how to network a physics simulation.
First Person Shooters First person shooter physics are usually very simple. The world is static and players are limited to running around and jumping and shooting.
Because of cheating, first person shooters typically operate on a client-server model where the server is authoritative over physics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spring Physics</title>
      <link>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/spring_physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/spring_physics/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Glenn Fiedler and welcome to Game Physics.
In the previous article we discussed how to simulate the motion of rigid bodies in 3D. Now we&amp;rsquo;re going to discuss how to implement spring physics.
The physics behind springs is simple but extremely versatile and useful. You can use springs to link points together to model rope and string, cloth, and even blobs of jelly. Springs can also be used to implement basic collision response, and to create joints that constrain the motion of rigid bodies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physics in 3D</title>
      <link>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/physics_in_3d/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/physics_in_3d/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Glenn Fiedler and welcome to Game Physics.
In the previous article we discussed how to integrate our physics simulation forward at fixed delta time increments, regardless of display framerate.
In this article we are going to simulate motion in three dimensions.
Rigid Bodies We will concentrate on a type of object called a rigid body. Rigid bodies cannot bend, compress or deform in any way. This makes their motion much easier to calculate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fix Your Timestep!</title>
      <link>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/fix_your_timestep/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/fix_your_timestep/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Glenn Fiedler and welcome to Game Physics.
In the previous article we discussed how to integrate the equations of motion using a numerical integrator. Integration sounds complicated, but it&amp;rsquo;s just a way to advance the your physics simulation forward by some small amount of time called &amp;ldquo;delta time&amp;rdquo; (or dt for short).
But how to choose this delta time value? This may seem like a trivial subject but in fact there are many different ways to do it, each with their own strengths and weaknesses - so read on!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integration Basics</title>
      <link>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/integration_basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://127.0.0.1:1313/post/integration_basics/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Glenn Fiedler and welcome to Game Physics.
If you have ever wondered how the physics simulation in a computer game works then this series of articles will explain it for you. I assume you are proficient with C++ and have a basic grasp of physics and mathematics. Nothing else will be required if you pay attention and study the example source code.
A physics simulation works by making many small predictions based on the laws of physics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>